Something strange is happening right
now. Everyone's talking about God again,
and people are more suspicious than
ever. They don't trust the media, they
don't trust institutions, and honestly,
a lot of that distrust didn't come out
of nowhere, but here's the danger. When
a culture loses confidence in truth,
people don't stop believing things, they
start believing almost anything. So now,
you have people opening the Bible again,
but carrying a worldview that distrusts
almost every authority claiming to speak
the truth. They're hungry for truth, but
they no longer know how to recognize it.
They want God, but they're suspicious of
authority. That's either going to become
one of the greatest openings for the
gospel in our lifetime, or one of the
most dangerous counterfeits of faith
we've ever seen. So how did we get here?
How did truth become suspicious right
when people started searching for it
again? That's what we need to talk
about. Let's get into it. Welcome back
to White's Disciples. My name is Nate,
and I'm helping you become the effective
Christian that you were meant to be. So
if people are searching for God again,
but they no longer know how to recognize
truth, well then we need to ask a deeper
question.
What happened to truth?
Right?
Because there was a time when truth was
not something that you created, it was
something that you discovered. Let's
begin with the ancient world. For the
Greeks, truth was not something that you
invented or customized,
it was something that you discovered
outside of yourself.
The Greek word often used for truth is
aletheia, the idea of something being
unconcealed or uncovered, right? Brought
into the light. The truth is what is
real when the shadows are removed.
That's why Plato's allegory of the cave
is so powerful. You have prisoners
chained inside a cave. They've been
there their whole lives. All they can
see are shadows moving on the wall. And
because they've never seen anything
else, they think the shadows are
reality.
But then, one prisoner is freed. He
turns around, and he sees the fire. And
then he walks outside and sees the sun.
And now he realizes, oh, what I thought
was real was only a shadow. Now, Plato
was not a Christian, but he understood
something important. Truth is not
whatever the prisoner feels while
staring at the wall. Truth is reality
outside the cave. Truth is above a
person. It has to be discovered. Now,
watch this. Several hundred years later,
Jesus walks into history and says
something that no Greek philosopher
could have imagined. I am the way and
the truth and the life. No one comes to
the Father except through me. Did you
catch that? Jesus doesn't say, I teach
the truth. He doesn't say, I know the
truth. He says, I am the truth. That
means truth is not ultimately an
abstract principle.
Truth is personal.
It has a face and a name.
Truth is the eternal Son of God who took
on flesh and dwelt among us. So, Plato
was right that truth is above us, but he
was wrong that truth is impersonal. The
ground of reality is not a form, as it
turns out. The ground of reality is the
Father.
And it's revealed through the Son by the
Spirit. That is why Christians have
always said, all truth is God's truth.
If something is true, it belongs to God.
That's moral truth, historical truth,
biblical truth.
If it actually corresponds to reality,
then it exists in the world God made and
is grounded in the God who cannot lie.
That's why truth sets you free.
It brings you out of the cave. It breaks
the chains. But then, something changed.
Humanity stopped looking upward for
truth and started looking inward. Now,
the Enlightenment was not all bad. There
were real advances in science and
medicine and politics, you know?
Christians are not against reason. God
gave us minds, all right? The problem is
not reason. The problem is when reason
tries to sit on the throne of
revelation. That's where the trouble
starts. René Descartes wanted certainty,
so he began by doubting everything he
could possibly doubt. His famous line
is, I think, therefore I am. Now,
Descartes was not trying to destroy
Christianity, but his method created a
shift. Instead of beginning with God and
revelation and a created order outside
the self, modern man increasingly begins
with the self.
My mind, my ability to verify. Do you
see the shift?
The The ancient person says, I must
conform myself to reality. The modern
person starts to say, reality must pass
through my verification system. And that
sounds harmless at first, but once the
self becomes the starting point,
the self eventually wants to become the
judge.
Reason becomes the new high priest.
Creation is no longer viewed primarily
as a theater of God's great glory. It
becomes a machine.
Precise and manageable.
Truth is still considered objective at
this point in time,
but it's been downgraded. It's been
lowered. It's no longer primarily
grounded in the creator. It's
increasingly grounded in creation,
reason, and human systems. And once
truth is lowered from God to human
reason,
it becomes vulnerable. Because human
beings are not neutral, as it turns out.
We are sinners.
And sinners do not merely reason.
Sinners suppress.
That's Romans 1 language, and we're
going to get there. But first, we need
to take the next step. Because
eventually people began to ask, what if
truth is not really about God? What if
truth is about power? Enter Karl Marx.
Marx changed the question. So, the older
question was, what is true? Marx's
question was, who benefits?
That is a massive shift.
Because once you make that move,
truth claims become suspicious. So, if
someone says this is true, Marx wants to
know whose interests does that serve?
Who gains power if everyone accepts this
as reality?
So, for Marx, religion, morality,
philosophy, and law all get interpreted
through class struggle.
The ruling class controls the ideas of
the age. And Christianity in his mind is
not divine revelation. It is a tool that
keeps oppressed people passive.
That's why he calls religion the opium
of the people. Now, somebody's thinking,
"Nate, are you saying that every concern
about exploitation is Marxist?" No, I'm
not saying that. The Bible actually
cares deeply about justice. James
rebukes the rich who exploit the poor.
The problem with Marx is not that he
notices oppression. The problem is that
he explains the human condition without
sin,
without God, and without the cross. That
means that he can identify a real
symptom while completely misdiagnosing
the disease.
And the diagnosis matters, friends. Marx
says that your beliefs are not
ultimately about truth. They are
products of your class position.
Your morality is not eternal. Your
religion is not revelation. It's all
social control.
So, truth becomes ideological. Then
Antonio Gramsci comes along and says,
"Well, actually, the real power is not
just who owns the factories, it's who
shapes common sense." And that's
schools, the media, and institutions.
These are the places where people learn
what is normal, what is acceptable, and
what is true. If you can control what a
society calls common sense, then you
don't need chains at all. You just need
narratives.
Right? And then the postmodernists came
along and finished the job. Michel
Foucault says truth and power are
inseparable.
Every society has what he called a
regime of truth.
So, in other words, what a society calls
true is bound up with its institutions
and power structures.
Teachers define knowledge, right? Judges
define crime. Now, Christians should not
be naive, okay? Can sinful people use
truth claims to manipulate? Of course.
Can institutions protect themselves?
Yes. The Bible says that happens all the
time. But, here's where Foucault goes
wrong. He does not merely say power can
distort truth.
I mean, Christianity says that. He moves
toward the idea that truth is produced
by power.
That's very different.
Because if truth is produced by power,
then truth is not something above us
that judges us.
Truth is something beneath us that we
manipulate. Then, Derrida comes along
with deconstruction.
He says that meaning is unstable.
Language is slippery. We never simply
access reality in a pure, uninterpreted
way. And, of course, the problem with
that is the person who says that meaning
is unstable expects you to understand
exactly what he means, right? Hey,
before we keep going, I want to tell you
about Wise Disciple Academy on Patreon.
This is where I'm building short,
practical training libraries for
Christians who want to think more
clearly, defend the faith, and speak
truth with wisdom the way that I do. You
can grab individual libraries like the
Truth Starter Library or the Apologetics
Starter Library as one-time purchases,
or you can get access to these resources
by joining one of the support tiers on
Patreon. And, that's basically how I
make these videos. So, if you want to go
deeper than YouTube, click the link
below or scan the QR code on the screen
and check out Wise Disciple Academy
today.
Postmodernism keeps sawing off the
branch that it's sitting on. Then,
Lyotard comes along and says
postmodernism is basically suspicion
toward metanarratives. A metanarrative
is a big story about reality. Now,
Christianity has a big story, right?
Creation, fall, redemption, and
restoration.
Well, the Enlightenment had a big story.
Reason leads to progress. Marxism had a
big story, right? Revolution leads to
liberation. Lyotard says, "We don't
trust those big stories anymore."
Why? Well, because big stories have
often been used to silence people. Now,
can people abuse grand narratives? Of
course, they can. But, Christianity does
not become false because sinners have
abused it. That's like saying marriage
is false because some husbands are
wicked. No, the abuse of a thing does
not disprove the thing. It It just
proves the sinfulness of the abuser.
But, once a culture loses confidence in
any shared story, what happens next?
You don't get one truth, you get a
thousand little truths.
My truth, your truth. Uh lived
experience becomes sacred. Identity
becomes authority. And disagreement
becomes violence. That's how we got
here. Truth went from something above us
to something inside us to something
created by power until finally people
began to say, "Truth itself is
oppression." And now we are living in
the wreckage. So, think about what
happens when a society believes this.
You know, if truth is oppression, well
then disagreement is not correction,
it's actually harm, right? If truth is
oppression, well then persuasion is not
love, it's actually violence. Think
about that. If truth is oppression, then
the Christian who says Jesus is Lord is
not making a truth claim,
he's making a power move. And that is
why people react with such intensity.
Think about that. Someone says Jesus is
the only way to God, and the response is
not, "Hmm, that's interesting. Why do
you believe that? Tell me more." The
response is, "How dare you?"
Why? Well, because the statement is not
being heard as truth, it's being heard
as domination. Now, let me be clear.
Christians must not be obnoxious, right?
We must not be cruel. We must not use
truth like a baseball bat and then
pretend that we're being persecuted when
people start ducking. Amen?
Peter says to give a reason for the hope
within us with gentleness and respect.
Paul says, "Speak the truth in love."
So, look, if you are arrogant, you need
to repent. But, if you are being
faithful,
don't be shocked when the world calls
truth hateful. Jesus told us this was
going to happen. The issue underneath
our cultural confusion is not merely
philosophical, it's spiritual.
And that takes us to Romans chapter 1.
Paul says, "For the wrath of God is
revealed from heaven against all
ungodliness and unrighteousness of men,
who by their unrighteousness suppress
the truth." Okay, hold on a second. So,
Paul does not say that human beings lack
access to truth. Did you notice that? He
says they suppress it.
That means the problem is not merely
intellectual, it's actually moral. It's
spiritual. People are not neutral truth
seekers who just need more data. We are
sinners who suppress what God has made
plain. Watch what he says. "What can be
known about God is plain to them because
God has shown it to them." So, creation
speaks. The world God made testifies to
the God who made it. But, instead of
honoring him as God or giving thanks,
Paul says they became futile in their
thinking and their foolish hearts were
darkened. Now, watch the progression.
So, they suppress the truth,
they refuse worship, their hearts become
darkened, claiming to be wise they
became fools, and then verse 25, they
exchanged the truth about God for a lie
and worshipped and served the creature
rather than the creator. That's it.
That's the whole story. That's Plato's
cave. That's expressive individualism.
that's our culture. That's you and me
apart from grace. See, humanity
exchanges the truth about God for the
lie. And this actually goes all the way
back to Genesis chapter 3. Adam and Eve
knew God.
They walked with God. God gave them a
command, and the serpent came along and
said, "Did God actually say?"
There it is, right? The first attack is
an attack on the word of God. Then the
serpent says, "You will be like God,
knowing good and evil." Now, something
about that. The knowledge of good and
evil is not merely information about
morality, it's moral autonomy. It's the
authority to determine good and evil for
yourself. That means the tree was not
about information.
It was actually about independence. The
lie was not merely, you know, go ahead,
eat the fruit. The lie was you can be
your own God.
You can define reality. You can decide
good and evil apart from the creator.
And Paul says in Romans 1, "That story
never stopped. Every generation reenacts
the fall over and over again. Every
sinner says, 'I know better than God.'"
Every culture says, "We will decide what
is true." And when that happens, you do
not get freedom, ladies and gentlemen.
You get darkness. Because when you
reject the creator, guess what? You
don't stop worshipping. You just start
worshipping something else.
Like the self. You worship whatever
gives you identity apart from God. But
you will worship, make no mistake about
it. You see, the human heart is not a
factory of neutrality, it is a factory
of idols. And that's why the solution is
not merely, "Let's be more reasonable."
Reason matters, by the way. Arguments
matter, but the deepest problem is not
lack of information. The deepest problem
is rebellion against God. So, how do we
get the truth back? We have to come back
to the one who is truth. Jesus does not
merely bring us a better philosophy. He
brings us back to reality.
He is the Logos, the word made flesh,
the one through whom all things were
made, the one who says, "I am the way
and the truth and the life." So, the way
back from confusion is not first a
political program, it's not an academic
theory, it's repentance and faith in
Jesus Christ. Now, somebody's thinking
at this point, "Nate, that's way too
simple." I get that, but simple doesn't
mean shallow. The gospel is actually
simple enough for a child to believe and
deep enough for the greatest minds in
history to spend the rest of their lives
contemplating. Amen? And if the problem
is that humanity has exchanged the truth
of God for the lie, well, then the
solution is not to just exchange one
ideology for another ideology, the
solution is to come home to God. So,
then what do we do? First, return to
Christ. Before we confront the world's
lies, we need to let the scripture
confront our own. Get in the word.
Belong to a faithful local church. Stop
letting the internet disciple you more
than Jesus Christ. Second, speak the
truth with courage and charity.
Not cowardice, not arrogance, courage
and charity. The world does not need
Christians who are afraid to speak, but
it also does not need Christians who
enjoy being harsh. We need truth with
love, clarity with humility. Third, make
disciples in a world of lies. Jesus did
not say, "Go win the comment section."
He said, "Go make disciples." Amen?
Arguments can win a moment, but
discipleship can shape a generation. So,
yes, Christians must answer objections
and dismantle arguments raised against
the knowledge of God. That's 2
Corinthians 10:5. But don't forget the
mission. We're not just trying to be
right out here. We're trying to be
faithful. In a world that says truth is
oppression, show the world the truth who
sets people free. Not by dominating
them, not by manipulating them, but by
dying for sinners and rising from the
dead. That's the difference. The world
uses truth claims to climb onto a
throne, but Jesus Christ is truth who
climbed onto a cross. And that's why he
alone can set us free. So is truth
oppression? No.
Lies are oppression. Sin is oppression,
right? Self-rule is oppression, but
truth? Truth is freedom because truth is
a person and his name is Jesus Christ.
All right, now I want to hear from you.
Where do you see this showing up the
most right now? Is it your school,
politics, social media, or even churches
from your vantage point? Let me know in
the comments below. If this video helped
bring clarity, please hit the like
button. It really does help YouTube push
this out to more people who need a
biblical perspective on these kinds of
conversations. And if you're brand new
to Wise Disciple, welcome. Thanks for
watching. Please consider subscribing.
This channel exists to help you become
the effective Christian you were meant
to be. All right, friends. I'll be back
with more videos soon, but in the
meantime, I'll say,
bye for now.